so we're going to discuss the offerings
that we make to the Buddhas and there's
a bunch of questions Ola had some good
questions you know can they see the
offerings why do you have to offer it if
they can see it all the time anyway
stuff like that okay so here we go uh
the
next verse uh and we're still in the
same chapter
[Music]
about yeah negative emotions and here's
the next part of the
chapter
uh
uh uh things to see things to hear
things to test and touch things to smell
and things there are are simply what
they are
they are like a city of Illusion a
mirage and like a dream okay uh the SR
words are uh G say Gandara G nag
nagara or nagar okay nagar is the
Sanskrit word for City okay so if you
know India there's lots of nagar like
bobnar the main diamond cutting business
in is in bbnagar
for example okay and uh Gandara is a
strange word because it
means uh Divine
musician and it also means
pra it also means Hungry Ghost so it's a
strange word Gandara means the musicians
of the Gods and Gandara also can mean uh
pishacha which means pra Hungry Ghost
okay
um and the idea is that as you approach
uh the city of the hungry ghosts where
hungry ghosts
live uh it looks from a distance like
there's a big city there and when you
get there it disappears okay so it's
similar to what happens with the hungry
ghosts when they see water or food from
a distance and then when they come up to
it it disappears okay they have this
that's how they live you can say the
kind of the definition of a Hungry Ghost
is a person who's chasing after their
dreams and then the dreams just keep
disappearing every time they get close
the the thing disappears and we all have
this experience we all have this kind of
thing so he when you say uh Gandara
nager it means uh I translate a city of
Illusion from a
distance it looks like a city when you
get close it disappears okay and that's
like a mirage and like a
dream uh so now we're talking about in
the medicine Buddha practice you're
supposed to attract them with big plates
of flowers and you know
ding-dongs little Donuts or stuff you
know
y
CH pon
uh you know you're supposed to attract
them with these offerings okay so what's
the nature of the offerings all right
and so again we're trying to look at the
medicine Buddha
practice uh with narus emptiness
understanding okay we're trying to look
at the medicine Buddha practice with
naran's understanding and I would
say if you don't understand thear and
you try to practice medicine Buddha it
won't work okay and you can do it I mean
you can do it as
a out of Blind Faith and it will work a
little bit uh but not much okay if you
understand the emptiness of everything
about the medicine Buddha practice if
you keep thinking about the emptiness of
it then then you'll be successful okay
you can cure people's illnesses with
medicine Buddha practice but I would say
only if you understand The Emptiness of
the practice and the illnesses okay all
right so even the offerings the bribes
that you offer to the medicine bu you
know hey look I got all these things for
you won't you help me out okay and uh
you have to understand that those
offerings themselves are coming from
your seeds okay and you have to
understand the nature of the offering
okay he says uh they are simply what
they are they are like a mirage they are
like a dream it looks like you bought
the offerings at the Safeway is it
around here in in Willcox Safeway it
looks like you bought them at the
Safeway but that's not true uh those
offerings came into your hands because
you shared what you had in the past okay
what
if you were not allowed to eat a
meal unless you served one to another
person
first okay three meals a day or whatever
two and a half okay what
if uh you can only get a meal if you
offer one to somebody else what if the
ratio is one to one what if you have to
give away one meal to get one meal okay
it's actually worse than that okay but
like that when you when you look at the
offerings understand that they didn't
come into your hands from the store they
came into your
hands by sharing what you have with
others I had this big you know lifetime
struggle with translation how to
translate things Donna parita the
Perfection
of some people say generosity I don't
like that word generosity means you're
not cheap
that's doesn't fit the word Donna okay
so first of all forget
generosity uh the Perfection of
generosity Perfection of giving is nice
but nowadays my my my understanding of
it is expanding into sharing the
Perfection of sharing what you have and
so when you are doing medicine budha
practice and even if you're just
offering an apple kind of an old old
will Cox
Apple uh offering it on the altar of
your diamond mountain
cabin uh try to think of how you got
that apple and then offer it okay and
that's a powerful Apple offering okay
and and in this medicine Buddha
practice even every time you do
something small like
offering even one little piece of fruit
uh your feeling about where it came from
has to be
correct like I I I I'll tell you a story
that's why you hired me because I'm so
old I have lots of
stories and uh I was
in my teacher's class in New Jersey in
1977 or
something like be long before teeny was
born there's a joke SP in English when
you were just a twinkle in your father's
eye it means your father was just
checking out your mom and okay like that
long ago
uh and I I'm sitting in this we had this
I built my teacher's house myself and it
it was twostory house and I I built it
and it was hard it was really hard to
build my hands are messed up from that
and uh it was winter
time so and then we didn't have money so
we bought these uh folding chairs for
people to sit in and they were cheap
wooden folding chairs and they were so
uncomfortable and he was a traditional
teacher so you had to
sit you know you couldn't move around
and you especially you couldn't ask
questions right oga you couldn't pester
the
questions just kidding questions are
good
uh but it was very painful to sit
through class and you're not supposed to
move and and you're not supposed to
interrupt him ever and uh and he kept
talking about the
emptiness of things you know and how
they're empty and I got impatient I
finally got he pushed me to the Limit
you know and I'm
like then he
the old the house I built for him was
connected to his old house so he had a
little house and then he had a big house
and they connected you know and I built
a door so he could go from his new house
to his old house and that door was like
a Magic
Door because the refreshments for class
were on the other side of the
door and so the whole
class I built a classroom and we're
sitting there on these uncomfortable
chairs and we're just thinking about the
other side of the door you know there's
lots whole table full of Refreshments he
used to really enjoy feeding his
students and beautiful offerings you
know like all kinds of cookies and cakes
and and it's just this white door
prevent me from reaching them you know
and I'm sitting through the whole class
you know I'm like
thinking about this door you know and
going through the door when he had a
break time I was just that was my focus
the whole class and
uh then I I was impatient in class and I
said he said okay let's take a break I
said can I just ask one question first
he said what and I said according to
you I don't understand the door like
when I look at the door I don't
understand the door according to you
I have ignorance or misunderstanding of
the door all the time you know but I'm
sitting here the door looks good to me
and it's a normal door there's good
stuff on the other side of the door and
I don't understand what I'm doing wrong
and and are you is the door not there
somehow and he said no the door is there
and then I said I don't understand what
just tell me what I'm doing wrong you
know stop teaching
philosophy and just tell me what I'm
doing wrong and I'll fix it you know and
and he said uh you think the door is
coming from the door and that's your
problem you know it's it's the door is
real and the door is preventing you from
your
Refreshments uh the door is real the
door is white the door is separated this
room from that room the door the door is
really there it is there that's not the
problem so I said I don't understand the
problem and he said how do you feel
about where the door came from is the
problem that's all that's all the door
is real the door is wide the door you
open the door you close everything's
real everything's okay
everything's as it seems It's a door it
looks like a door theun of the do is to
keep you out of that room you know it
works but the way you feel about where
it came from is wrong you know that's
your ignorance that's your
misunderstanding where did the door come
from I said I know where the door came
from I bought it at the lumber store I
went to the lumber store in Lakewood New
Jersey you know I picked it out I got it
on the truck I drove the goddamn truck
here I put the took the door off off the
truck I I laid the door I screwed the
door me and hungar put the door up I
know where the door came from he said
that's not where the door came from and
that's your problem you know you think
the door came from the lumber store the
door didn't come from the lumber
store and the offerings you make to
medicine Buddha are the same as the door
okay how are they real yes can you sneak
some for quality control before you
offer them
you don't want to offer unquality
controlled
offerings I think it's your Buddhist
responsibility to Quality Control no I
mean the dingdong package might be
broken open anyway uh yeah they're real
everything's fine but they did not come
from the store okay and if you feel like
they came from the store you're
infecting your offerings to the Buddha
okay you're offering the Buddhist
something it's like offering them poooo
or something okay a door which you think
about the wrong way is a pooo door you
know you invite the Buddhist for dinner
and you think the food came from the
store you might as well offer them poo
poo Okay because it's polluted it's it's
it's dirty there's something wrong with
the offering got it if you if you can
keep you don't have to sit there every
two minutes during your s then say Oh
the the Apple came from me the Apple
came from me it's going to interrupt
your practice okay but you have to have
this emotion or this feeling that the
reason I was able to offer an apple is
because I gave an apple to a human being
in the past Okay the reason I can offer
an apple Apple to an enlightened being
is I shared my apples with hungry people
in the past okay then then that apple is
a good offering that apple is a sweet
offering if you get an
Apple from the store from the
seeds of serving apples to starving
people in Africa or something that's a
real offering and and that that Apple
came from the right place okay got it
okay apples which you got by sharing are
worthy to offer okay apples which you
don't share are not worthy of offering
okay got it that's Nara and then that's
practicing medicine Buddha with
Nar okay we're inviting Nara Into The
Retreat room to do our medicine Buddha
pregnant okay and if he's not sitting
next to you you got a problem if you
think think you bought the Apple so you
have a problem okay got
it it's your feeling about the door
that's wrong it's not the door the door
is fine you did buy it at the lumber
store and okay I mean it was such a
big event in my life when he said that
I'm like ah good I'm not supposed to
pretend the door's not there I'm not
supposed to think the door is illusion
it says here illusion right city of
Illusion
Ganda nagara you know the the the city
of the Hungry Ghost you know that's not
the point that's not what makes it a
losery it's aery because it looks like
you bought it but you
didn't you had the money to buy it
because you always share what you have
with other
people and and that means okay you
ready that means hesitating to share is
the stupidest thing in the world okay
like I always make these ridiculous
offerings when my wife comes to diam
Mountain the first half hour is always
honey I'm sorry I gave away $10,000 to
John Brady yesterday she's like w you
know no she doesn't do that she's like
Yay really she is okay but uh there's a
hesitation right like maybe if I do that
too much I won't have any money after
that I wrote to Ellie I said do I have
that much
money
right didn't I she's like
yeah okay
so that hesitation to to to present an
offering uh means you don't understand
where the offering came from in the
first place okay when you hesitate to be
generous it means you don't understand
why you have the money in the first
place it came from off the reason you
have $10,000 to give John Brady is
because you offered money
before okay otherwise you wouldn't have
the
M where's the
Box
um can you please talk
about when we're making offerings to
medicine Buddha or we're
practicing uh the Perfection of
giving the power
of
um not being concerned with receiving a
result and and C can you can you speak
on that just the the power of remaining
in the act of of of giving or sharing
and not being worried about oh I'm gonna
get this and how maybe that could be a
form of grasping they worrying about oh
I'm going to get
a
b or new house you know yeah thank you
it comes up in DCI so in DCI you know we
go on these tours
to koala lumur in
2025 and
joobu and Singapore I hope I mean
Orchard Road
shopping with me and Jenny right uh okay
uh we did make a deal from 25 um you
know if
I so we in DCI we go around teaching
people that uh your business will be
successful if you understand the
emptiness of the business and The
Emptiness of the business is that if you
are generous with the money you get your
business will be more successful okay
then the question
is isn't that a kind of attachment and
doesn't that kind of mess up the process
you know if the reason you are generous
to people is just because you want a new
car okay does that mess up the giving
and by the way in the beginning of the
maika avatara the great great commentary
to n by chandi okay he asked that
question he said he it's a very
interesting question he says if your
generosity is polluted by
self-interest does it still work and and
Chanda kirti who's the greatest in the
after n he says of course it still
works it's like watch okay
uh uh I'm thinking about giving John
Brady more money but Tim needs it worse
uh okay
ready did the did the rosary
drop uh now I'm thinking about Not
Giving either one
anything you know now I'm thinking about
how famous I'm GNA get if I give him a
lot of
money now I'm thinking I'll just do it
without telling
anybody you know it still works okay
gravity Works no matter how you feel
about it okay and giving sharing with
others it works uh regardless of how you
feel about it okay even if it's selfish
it still works that's that's a very
basic Buddhist question if your
motivation is to get famous if your
motivation is to make more money for
yourself
uh it still works okay it still works it
doesn't work as
well okay it's a lot
slower okay and it's a lot smaller than
if you did it with your whole heart you
know okay but it still works gravity
works if you're in a good mood or a bad
mood you know you know it doesn't
gravity doesn't care okay so that's the
answer to that you know it's okay
and by the way I
mean if I just
say I I do not say you should give
away what you have without thinking that
you might get something I do not say
that I say it's
fine but you should say everybody should
get a
Mercedes why think small okay if I give
this money to to
ACI so that they can survive next year I
hope I get a Mercedes and I hope
everyone else does too then it's
Buddhism okay then it's Buddhism you can
have a Mercedes it's okay but you got to
make sure everyone gets what okay that's
okay you can't in English they say you
can run but you can't hide okay if
you're generous the Mercedes are going
to chase
you okay I'm sorry sorry I keep giving
away cars and then I keep getting more
cars okay it's the way it
goes we gave the Ukrainian ladies and ni
a new car better than my car they have a
hybrid 23 Toyota rap 4 if you want to
trade cards you let me
[Music]
know okay anyway thank you for the
sponsors who did that yeah and that it
was very sweet the only problem
is they read the wrong driver
manual and then they took the test and
every state is different right so they
read the Florida driver man in Florida
everything's
backwards but I'm sure next year they're
going to drive here all right okay don't
smash my new
car all right and by the way thank you
to the sponsor who did that that was
really beautiful okay uh
next next item is very
beautiful
Tada my uh photo agency that I buy the
photos from there's certain photos they
don't
sell like I tried to find a dead person
they don't sell it it's weird right I
don't know what it is is they won't sell
you a picture of a dead person I'm like
okay I'll make one with my AI then the
AI says cannot make this
picture not acceptable picture okay but
uh I found this one okay and uh there's
a big debate about offerings okay
there's a big debate about offering
we're talking about medicine Buddha
practice we are getting ready to do
we're getting ready for the big moment
in the S when we tell the medicine
Buddhist put up or shut
up it means give me what you promised or
get out of here okay you made these big
promises each medicine Buddha made a
promise four promises eight promises you
know we're getting to the part n where
you say okay I'm ready now do it okay
and then they're like well I don't off
today's a good day you know and you're
like wait you promised you know didn't
you make a promise okay and supposed to
be we're making these offerings the gist
says will you offer the best offerings
you can you know should you offer tired
old
apples that feel like rubber or or
should you offer a really good quality
Apple you know he says does it matter
you know do they care they don't care
okay you offered them an old Apple or a
new Apple they have total Bliss okay
they don't care okay but you should care
okay they should be the best offerings
you can and then the gar poses a
question is a fresh Apple only fresh if
you have rotten apples in the same
world is a is a beautiful crisp fresh
Apple only beautiful crisp and fresh in
a world where you have also rotten
apples are thing are offerings beautiful
only by
comparison is the world relative is is
is is it relative is everything relative
or Not by the way Einstein talked about
relativity that's different and if you
want a electron now I'll give you one
someday uh but that's a different thing
okay is it
possible to perceive an apple as fresh
and
beautiful without ever seeing a rotten
apple or an old Apple are things
absolute is the quality of things
absolute or can you only perceive Beauty
in a world where there's also ugliness
you see that's a question and and the
guardian is going to answer it okay it's
a very beautiful
question
can you only see a
beautiful can you only see food as
healthy and
healthy and beautiful in a
world can you only see food is healthy
and beautiful in a world where you have
thrown
up okay it is it only people who have
thrown up from from bad food who can
appreciate good food you know is it
relative okay and and I'll leave it open
to
discussion okay I'll leave it open to
discussion I'll give you a question you
know we're supposed to make the best and
most beautiful offerings we can and the
practice will work better if we by the
way don't go to the grocery store with
my teacher to buy offerings and let
unless you want to spend four or five
hours you know
unbelievable he handle every package of
cookies in the store you know one by one
he's
like you know and really really I mean
it drive me crazy I'm at the end of the
counter I'm
going and he's like these cookies look
like they might be older and I'm like I
don't check
day
and and really and he had certain
medicine Buddha like certain cookies and
Medicine G doesn't like how he knows I
don't
know but it's amazing okay so is it
relative or not what do you guys think
can you only tell high quality cookies
if you see lousy cookies or can you tell
high quality cookies without seeing
lousy cookies is is it relative or is it
not relative is it absolute is Cookie
quality absolute or is Cookie quality
relative what do you guys think there's
an answer back
there watch The Box careful careful
Tracy watch
careful make sure everybody's looking
before you throw the
Box otherwise somebody might achieve
Satori okay wouldn't the offering be
empty itself it's just same Parts you
put together differently so depending on
who's looking it would be beautiful or
not so I can only know the apple is good
because I see different apples as well
but someone like a Buddha will
probably put all the parts in a
beautiful way to see everything
beautiful so I think your answer is for
a non Buddha it's relative uh to to tell
that an apple is crisp and fresh you
have to have an experience of apples
that are not crisp and fresh but if
you're a Buddha since you're always
going to see all the apples that's crisp
and fresh even the ones that are not uh
it's not it's absolute that's that's her
answer okay other
opinion wait what's Al either dancing or
she's having some
realizations her boyfriend's name hakeim
you
know just
kiding I think that uh we we can
experience uh something as pleasant or
unpleasant without uh knowing or having
seen something otherwise but we cannot
give the name to what we experience
without having seen something different
from that yeah okay okay so I think what
what you said was we
can
experience uh an apple as crisp without
meeting apples that are
rubbery but to name it crisp we need to
have the name rubbery to distinguish
between them something like that I think
so yeah okay anybody else
yeah
uh I think the Apple The Taste is good
or bad depends the person the SE uh that
means if they taste the apple is a good
taste that means they offer some good
food to somebody before if the taste the
apple is a bad taste and they might give
the that food to someone before so I
think whatever the feeling is depends
they offer things to someone Def and
give the feeling to someone so I I'm
going to I'm gonna add something to what
you said if that's
true then the beauty of the offerings is
absolute it's not relative okay you
don't have
to experience a lousy Apple to
experience a beautiful outut I if that's
how I understand what you're saying and
I agree with you I agree with you if you
have good seeds you will have good
apples to offer if you have bad seeds
you'll have better apples to offer but
you don't have to experience bad apples
to experience Good Apples if you have
all these good seeds you would always
have good apples and I would say that
there's some things in the world that we
have that are already that way and we
don't see the other side we we never
experienced it's the B one you see that
mean okay it's absolute I say it's if
it's coming from seed it's absolute okay
you which implies you can have a
heaven where there's no rotten apples
got yes so um I I remember I heard this
story from a very very old grandpa from
Israel he live in Israel he was surviv
Holocaust so he always eat just very
rotten food and nobody can change any
all of them their rarely kids try to
help him but he told that when I was
like when it was 4 War I and I was
Holocaust this is the only food what we
ate so for me it's the best and he
cannot eat fresh or good food just
because this is for him was a real and
uh he never changed so he didn't know
the other test taste maybe he knew
before but then he like so you're in the
absolute school you're in the Jenny Wong
Michael Roach
school okay all right let's keep let's
go on okay now uh let's see what the
garer says okay next uh I think
it's EDM 5.31 here's
the uh being attracted is just a thing
we attribute based on what is not
attractive Jenny the guardian is against
us okay he says something like an
attractive apple is just a name you make
up based on an Apple that's not
attractive if all apples were attractive
there wouldn't be a word
attractive so that's kind
of that's kind of what she said
the words you
know if all apples
were delicious there wouldn't be a word
delicious right if there's no such thing
as bad taste word then there's no word
for delicious right if all the apples
are the same how would you tell it was
delicious anyway he said the guardian
says being attractive is just a thing we
attribute based on what is nonattractive
okay neither is the unattractive not
something relative uh unattractive is
also relative he says not absolute okay
why uh
because you can't tell something's
unattractive if you don't know what's
attractive you can't tell something's
attractive you can't call something a
good apple if you never met a bad apple
and if you and you can't call something
a bad apple if you never met a good
apple okay I don't believe it I don't
think that's what he's saying
okay I think if you have the seeds to
eat have delicious apples all the time
that's okay okay and I would say
Buddhist after when you make an offering
of a soggy
Apple to a medicine Buddha they perceive
it as a perfect Apple how done okay all
right they don't have the karma to see a
s
Apple okay got it my opinion still you
should buy the best
ones and and I I think the great
teachers like my
teacher uh it's not unimportant to them
it's very important to them he will go
to the store for three four hours he he
send me to the store for for everything
except his
offerings and then the offerings he has
to buy I have to drive him to the store
he he said offerings I it's my
department you don't touch the offerings
okay that's my department you can you
can buy my food but you can't buy the
offerings right so take your time and
make them beautiful okay take your time
and and make sure your offerings are
awesome it's not an unimportant thing
it's a very important thing okay and I
think also uh in my
opinion uh a good offering is anonymous
you know like there's
a story about a llama who used to buy
soggy apples and offer them before he
closed his Retreat door so when his
friends come to see the offerings they
don't look fancy they look old and then
when they leave he puts the real
offerings on because he doesn't want to
be influenced by Pride he he doesn't
want to think I have the best apples or
something like that the best offering I
ever made in my life was a diamond on an
altar and I hid it on the Altar and no
one ever saw it except my llama found it
like within an hour uh
uh but uh or 10 minutes okay I mean I
hit it very carefully and he's like
why'd you put that diamond on your
I'm so I think uh there's a there's a
beauty of a of an offering being
anonymous okay and nobody knows you're
making offering so that's a
beautiful that's a beautiful offering
Jesus said something like that what is
that don't advertise your spiritual
practice if you're fasting today one day
fast try not to look
hungry like so your friends will say oh
joy why you look so hungry and you say
oh I'm
fasting I'm doing a one day vow you know
like you're supposed to try to Le normal
okay all
[Music]
right
yeah mention at the beginning that when
we offer Apple um bro it good apple with
a misunderstanding it's just like a pooo
to offer yeah and then um but so when we
um offer a p to yeah I mean just maybe
my question sounds like not that
attractive um but I I was thinking um
and asking what if we um offer PO with
the understanding with good
visualization because every time we are
living in a like normal
life normal day normal people we pool we
eat we do everything normal but we need
to turn this into practices so um if I
offer po to someone with uh good
intention with understanding and with
um visualization yeah yeah so is it a
good thing to offer to someone higher
it's possible yeah it's possible but um
for them was like feel very weird well
I'll tell you a story
okay uh there's a famous story uh there
was a student who got a diamond way
initiation and he got initiation into
baa practice so some high tantric de you
know and and his teacher gave him uh
initiation then he
said Rangel Rangel what's that high it's
a high principal in Tantra
rang say
rang very high teaching in t Rangel
means once you got that initiation
believe you are B and nobody can shake
your belief if your llama say I made a
mistake you're not B you say I'm sorry
it's too
late I'm already don't tell B it's not B
it's too late okay rang means
believe it when you got an initiation
and they made you vaj yogini nobody can
take that back nobody the Llama who gave
it to you cannot take it back it's too
late you already vaj what are you gonna
make vaj
not you know it doesn't work so that's
called tantric practice has two high
principles one rang Rangel means I am
bogini and I have people all the time
telling me you're not and I'm saying
you know I am I'm sorry you know you can
tell me all day you're just wasting your
breath I got initiation I am B okay so
the student got bar I am bar and he got
WR sell is the other half song means
picture yourself that way in cool ways
okay picture yourself that way in cool
ways you know so vaji yogini likes to
wear
then put little vagini stuff on your
body okay maybe your underwear is red
okay like don't tell anybody you know do
do little things uh that remind you who
you are I had a friend David Stump right
sardak husband he used to paint his uh
fingernail red you know and when he went
to the grocery store everybody's
like but say I want to remember who I am
you know sang means uh the image keep
the image in your mind something small
keep something small you know do
something special for
example uh always lead with your left
when when you get on a escalator or
stairs or you step into a shop always
step with your left foot first okay
that's sell N Sell N means uh little
physical signs that you are her and
don't tell anybody just don't if you
watch me step on here it's always a left
foot now I told
you I might do right tomorrow just to
think but uh that's called song okay
little so there's a story that um this
disciple was is practicing B really hard
he got the initiation he's picturing
himself as believe self identification
WR I am bar I am bar this the teacher
say you're not he I am you know I am you
gave me initi after that moment I'm B
I'm sorry you can't take it back and
that's true okay I am B then I have
little things you know I do things left
hand I I I I I step with the left foot
first these are little signs of who I am
okay and and they're beautiful signs and
I spend my whole life like that I have
many many little weird superstitions
like that okay and and I keep
them and I do them so
anyway wait I'm not there
yet then the the Gandhi they they beat
the Gandhi Gandhi is a big uh
board six feet long 2 meters okay as
long as the armspan of a large person
which is 2
me and you're supposed to
sorry you're supposed to put the Gandhi
stick on your left shoulder and then you
hit
it like and it has to be teak wood or
hardwood and this was before
metal it was the
Bell uh for the Monk's confession before
metal before metal was common before
anybody had metal like thousands of
years ago they had a stick and you put
it on your shoulder and you
go and that means come to confession
okay so trce some so anyway the student
was sitting there having breakfast with
the teacher and they hit the Gundy they
still do it at my mon they still use a
gundi nobody can hear
it we keep a good eye on our clocks so
so he hit the Gundy and the teacher said
let's go time for SoJO the student said
Bova doesn't go to
SoJO B was perfect
already I'm sorry I got nothing to
confess B don't need to go to sojong the
teacher grab him by the ear and pull him
to sojong he said yes you are goddamn B
but you're going to
soj understand
in theory you could offer poo
poo with the enough
motivation in
practice you
know probably your teacher gonna pull
you here no it's definitely possible and
we have many offerings like that there
are such offerings uh it's possible but
it takes a lot of practice you know that
student was too young
he just got by this morning then he
decided you don't have to go confess
anything in the
t-shir so uh in theory it's possible in
practice it's very difficult but it's a
goal the goal is done the goal is
done yeah yeah yeah and that everything
becomes a great offer yeah so that's the
goal but it takes many years of practice
and you still have to go to
surgery okay all right Tim what's up
what's the
schedule oh my God okay I was kind of
leading everything up to that okay let's
do
that you um let me do up to we'll do 15
minutes of Q&A is that okay is that
good
no uh at at 8:45 we'll do 15 minutes of
Qing is that right am I right okay all
right uh next item you guys 5.32
Francisco yeah uh I call this going
deeper into the offerings okay like
unwrapping the offerings and trying to
understand them better we're still on
the subject of offerings what's coming
up for the rest of the
week we're gonna do the seven
preliminaries again this time just for
the a medicine Buddha
dudes and and
then uh we're going to start calling in
their
promises okay hey you said if someone
recites your name seven times you know
all the people in this world who are
imprisoned right now anywhere in a house
with a family or in a jail or they
should they should start to be free they
should start to get Freedom okay like
that okay you you promise
okay so we are that's where we're going
we're going to those promises and we're
going to The Emptiness of those promises
okay because that's how they work got it
but we got to finish this offering thing
first if the teacher sneaky they might
teach you emptiness in the offerings
before you get to the
promises okay here we go next
one uh yesterday we had the four
mudras uh they're called the four
seals
uh in English you call seal of
approval right like the health
department has to stamp the food if the
or especially medicine if the medicine
has a government approval and you can
take it if not you can't fell it okay in
Buddhism there's four seals of approval
okay and we talked about them
yesterday and the idea
is something like
that those four
qualities of a
Buddhist those four qualities that make
words the word of the Buddha okay we
talked about them yesterday in Tim's
class there are four things that make
words the word of the Buddha okay do
they teach emptiness do they teach
suffering do they teach emptiness what's
the fourth
one do they teach about Nirvana okay uh
those are the four seal they're called
mudra mudra means seal of approval okay
it's a stamp from the Buddha
Department uh then that teaching is
approved okay and
and the tradition in in Buddhism is
don't waste your time on a book or a
teaching if it doesn't address these
four at least one of them it can be
directly or it can be indirectly but if
it doesn't talk about any of those
things don't waste your time because you
don't have time as I said
yesterday figure out the death thing
first and then do the rest of stuff then
get your
Tesla okay like figure out the don't
figure out how to get a Tesla and then
save the figuring out your death for
later figure out your death first and
then figure out how to get a test okay
like take care of the death thing first
and and so he's talking here about the
idea of impermanence or or changing okay
and it's if it is something wrong to
look at something changing and call it
rather unchanging he's talking about
chii these are the four big mistakes
okay the four big mistakes the the first
one is to look at a body which is
falling apart already and believe you're
going to last for a
while okay to look at your body and say
I'm not as old as gisha at least and and
think that you're going to last for a
while is ignorance okay lots of young
people die before old people okay you to
look at your body and say I still have
some time is a big mistake okay that's
like the first big mistake of Buddhism
okay to think you have some time left
you didn't get cancer yet well actually
we don't know do
we so uh he says if it's wrong to look
at a body which is constantly falling
apart and feel like I still have some
time okay if that's a
mistake
then would it be wrong to think that
emptiness itself is never
changing because there's nothing
changing about it isn't a mistake when
there's something changing about
something to think of that thing as
unchanging I'll say it again is it a
State when there's something changing
about your body to think that it's
unchanging yeah that's classic not
Buddhist okay they're like oh I'm if I
have green drinks I'll live
[Music]
forever you know that's classic wrong
idea in Buddhism just think that you're
GNA last for a while it's a classic
wrong idea now in the G says is it wrong
to think you're not changing when you're
changing every
second when your body's falling apart
every
day you know when it's the nature of
your body to fall apart and then you
think you're going to last for a while
is that
ignorance is that a bad attitude yeah
it's a bad attitude by the way you're
not supposed to get scared okay it's not
about done you're not supposed to say oh
my God I might have cancer I can't tell
you know people like that you know
they're always going to the do I have
cancer or not they're like I don't know
it could be one cell we don't know you
know so it's a
healthy understanding that your body is
falling apart and use it for something
cool and enjoy it while you have it okay
so it's not like oh I'm falling apart
I'm a bad person it's not like that are
you falling apart yes are you a
beautiful person yes okay are you
falling apart right now yes yes are you
the sexiest most beautiful being in the
universe uhhuh yeah okay okay that's
Buddhism that's really Buddhism okay
yeah you're falling apart yeah inside
it's all poop scrape the supermodel skin
underneath it's all poop you
know but still to have this body is
super special you know you're on your
way to Buddha hood you know like
nobody's gonna stop you okay so you got
some snot it okay
hey okay it's beautiful it's a beautiful
messed up body okay all right so he says
but is it wrong to think your body's
going to last for a while when it's not
yes that's wrong then he says it's the
opposite
true okay is it wrong to think that
emptiness never changes because it
doesn't do you have to think that
everything in the universe is
impermanent is that one of the four
mudra is it one of the four seals of a
Buddhist teaching yes that everything is
impermanent then yeah all cost thing
good is emptiness
impermanent
no can you destroy emptiness and by the
way you want subtle and permanence here
it is you want subtle subtle and
permanence here it is okay okay somebody
asked
me you want the normal explanation of
subtle improvements or you want the
deeper
one I
mean our classes we do the real one okay
normal subtle
impermanence
uh is called high school
reunion okay and you know you go back in
America 25 years after you graduate you
go you go back and have a meeting with
your friends what's the first thing you
say oh you look you look just the same
you know and the reason you say that is
they
don't oh you haven't changed a bit and
they're like there's nothing up here I
used to have hair you don't remember you
know they're oh well maybe that changed
yeah uh so there's this thing about
subtle impermanence
uh gross impermanence you notice every
five years or something you know my hair
isn't what it used to be but subtle
impermanence is going on every
millisecond the hair didn't get gray on
the last day of the five years the hair
got gray every minute up to the end of
the five years okay uh it's like that
some people explain sther permanence
that way but if you want the deeper one
is is emptiness impermanent or not and
that's that's where I have a problem
with the word
impermanent okay is emptiness
impermanent or
not okay this this rosary is coming from
the seeds in my mind in your mind okay
this rosary is coming from the seeds in
your mind what's the emptiness of it
it's not coming without those things
okay The Emptiness of this rosary is you
cannot be this
rosary uh if you don't have the seeds
for it okay this rosary is
not not coming from seeds Okay this
rosary is not not coming from seeds and
that's never changes unchanging constant
it never changes it's never true that
this rosary is a little bit less coming
from seeds today than yesterday there's
no such thing e either it's coming from
your seeds or it's not coming from your
seeds there's no middle thing you can't
say ah today it's like 80% from seeds
and 20% not from seeds that's how
Buddhists live their life by the way
with the people who irritate them are
they coming from your say well
mostly you know forget the well mostly
okay the 100% okay so the truth of this
rosary is that uh it's not not coming
from your Saints does that mean it can't
be
destroyed every real
Buddhist every you want to know what a
real retreater is someone who ran around
their Retreat cabin looking for 108
beats you know youi did it right the
string breaks they all
go then you're under the all the
furniture and you're like I got 106
where like that okay the rosary will
finish it'll be broken I'll lose a be
you know and everybody who ever did long
retreat that's one of the activities is
is looking for the beads after the
stream broke okay this it's not
permanent it will it will go out of
existence emptiness is
unchanging emptiness can
go out of existence when the thing which
has the emptiness goes out of existence
that's all okay The Emptiness of this
rosary will go out of existence on the
day that you know the string breaks and
all the beads Mo around okay you can't
find them the the lamest what do you
call kind of the weirdest thing in
Retreat is to try to put beads from one
rosary on another rosary and it just
looks weird okay so can this end yes can
its emptiness
End by the way we we never use the word
ending we use the word go out of
existence okay and that's subtle
impermanence if you really want to
understand s impermanence and by the way
nobody else can teach it to you I'll bet
and I'm not bragging I'm just saying
it's the way it is okay when when you
destroy the rosary it's emptiness
goes out of existence it is not
destroyed destroyed
means okay and that's not how emptiness
stops emptiness
[Music]
goes Bop gone okay emptiness doesn't get
less empty and then die there's no such
thing we don't say and we don't say wear
out we say goes out of it blinks out of
existence when the Rosary hits the bu
okay got it and that's subtle
impermanence and you got to cook
it go box who's got the
box and by the way if you can understand
if you can think about that it'll help
you see emptiness
directly the the beads can go the beads
can wear out the beads can Decay the
beads can get older and older and then
die but the emptiness of the beads does
not
it lasts until the last it lasts until
the millisecond that the string breaks
okay got it go ahead so does that mean
that our Buddha nature which is in
Emptiness is the only
permanent uh that's a good question
uh is is anything let's say
Everlasting is there anything
Everlasting in the universe besides
emptiness and we say there are there are
some things uh empty space for example
okay
whether whether the empty space in which
our present Universe
stands is filled by matter flying around
from The Big Bang or whether that matter
all reaches what you called U heat heat
death okay no more information
processing the world the atoms of the
universe are now equally spaced
throughout the Universe and there's no
movement there's no longer any heat uh
which means there can no longer be
information because there's no movement
of particles they're all equally spaced
apart uh that's the end of the of this
universe but the
background space in which those
particles stand is unchanging and if all
those particles disappeared the
background location of them would never
change so location doesn't ever change
and cannot go out of existence okay but
emptiness can go out of existence
because it's attached to a certain
object right but in this instance the
very specific instance of The Emptiness
of my mind yeah that that will never go
out of exist because my mind has always
been and will always be yeah that
emptiness will never go out of existence
because the object is attached to yeah
exactly thank you cool we got a few more
minutes for questions talk
loud well okay um so my question is um I
tend to take things literally so when I
hear that everything comes from me um I
question it I I still wondered want to
learn more about it um like the the
nuclear bombs and the wars and all the
violence um so five years ago you may
know my sister was killed by one or two
men in Jamaica my sister was older than
me she's my only sister and she was
always a very difficult person in my
life and she hated that I looked like
the good girl and she looked like the
bad girl um and after her she died in
November of 2018 and I don't know much
about the circumstances um and so I've
really thought a lot about it and I've
had you know I help people in grief
that's my work and I want to learn more
about did did that come from
me um I don't know I just uh it's a
struggle it was a very violent death it
was Suffocation and um being bound and
gagged and married show grave and has
been really a challenge for me to
understand after I I realized that I
really did love her um and these
teachings have helped me so
much okay
uh here's how I was taught to answer
this question and and I lived with my
teacher for 25 years all day every day
you know and I was the
you know I took care of
everything everything so I I was with
him all day and except when I went to
work or something like that and um so
one of my jobs because we lived at this
Mongolian
Temple people would come to visit the
temple you know and
uh and all kinds of people would come to
visit the temple and and he was
busy reading translating he said you
take take care of the people who I'm
like okay and uh people would come to
visit and uh I found out
quickly that the kind of questions they
would ask and I and I asked them to help
me I would ask him you know what I how
should I answer this question one
question is
swastika okay uh this symbol of a
swasti yeah in uh
SW
[Music]
means Su means goodness a
means is means
n swastika means goodness permanent
goodness okay and we always put a
swastika on the teacher SE in Buddhism
we and at our Temple we always had four
sasas on the on the teacher's seat it
represents the long life of the teacher
it means the long successful life of the
teacher we have to put a swastika four
swastikas on the teacher's seat and you
will see anytime you go to a real
Buddhist temple they should have four
sasus on the teacher seat so you can
guess what happened we live next to a
Jewish
town we live next to Lake New Jersey
lewood New Jersey is conservative Jewish
town it's all guys with the hats and
these things what do you call them or
super Orthodox and they would come to
visit the temple and they would see the
SW what's that you know and we're like
oh and then we'd have to explain to them
what's a what's a swasti you know and uh
they were okay with it you know very
rarely someone would get angry you know
we say Hitler stole it from India don't
worry about it long 2,000 years before
Hitler we were making SWAT okay and he
stole it but it's a beautiful sign and
it's a it's a it means a good thing and
don't worry about it okay then they
would start asking about the
Holocaust you know who killed all these
people you know why would they kill you
know what's your opinion what's the
Buddhist opinion you know the real
Buddhist opinion is you cannot be
killed unless you have killed someone
else that's the Buddhist
opinion you cannot be killed unless you
killed someone else it's not possible
it's
impossible uh then I saw the first
Jewish group that came I said you can't
be killed unless you killed someone
before and they got really angry you
know and I was like whoa and I went I
went and I asked my teacher I said I
told them what you told me that you
can't be killed unless you killed
somebody and he said big
mistake he's like never talk like that
you know to a Jewish group it's not it's
a very big mistake say anytime they come
here you should say something about
impermanence or I don't know but never
ever a mother's
child dies in a car accident and you
tell the mother that the child killed
someone in their past life what kind of
Cruelty is that you know what kind of
terrible thoughtless thing to say to a
mother that your child died because they
killed someone in your past life what a
terrible thing to you'll probably die in
your P you know so I mean there's
certain that's why
Buddha taught three turnings of the
wheel that's why Lord Buddha softened
his message depending on the audience
okay the whole Abid Dharma is a softened
message he never taught emptiness in in
the first 30 years of his life he didn't
teach anybody an emptiness what he
didn't remember or you know uh he didn't
want to hurt people so I when we think
about why people died when we talk about
why people died
never forget what I learned as the
temple tourist guide you know I was the
temple tourist guide you know and he
taught me how to talk to people and he
said you gotta check out the people and
you got to check out how they feel and
you have to teach to their level you
cannot you cannot there are certain
things you cannot say to
people that are hurt you know you cannot
say those things you have to understand
uh when to say things and when not
there's there's an appropriate time to
talk about death that way and there's a
many many appropriate times not to talk
about that that way and and you have to
think about it okay you have to think
about it it depends on how you have to
judge the strength of the person okay
you have to judge the strength of the
person okay and uh but here's one more
suggestion when you're answering a
question like that
Karma doubles in power every 24 hours
okay if you give $1 today with correct
motivation it's $2 million in 30 days
okay you you give $1 to a poor person
with the right
motivation you have just inserted a $2
million of seeds in your mind okay
within 30 days it has become $2 million
okay we'll come back to you yeah this is
karma okay and and you can do the math
okay all you can do it on your cell
phone I do it sometimes when I forget
the
number uh I go 1 time 2 * 2 * 2 time two
so one hand I go one two three four I go
up to 30 one time two * two * two 2 *
two and I think it's 2 million you can
check it out on your cell phone you can
check it out but uh seeds double in
power every 24 hours
so what that
means is that
uh there's a very famous example in
scripture why do monks do summer ret
treat V why did they do summary
treat yeah
traditionally uh monks were supposed to
do three Monon Retreat every
summer so they wouldn't step on the bugs
who come up in the summer okay because
in the summer there's more bugs so the
tradition of Summer Retreat which we
still keep in the
monastery uh stay indoors for three
months don't walk around outside because
there's going to be more bugs that you
will kill okay and that's called unaware
killing unaware killing you you don't
see every bug you step on
okay but logically you understand it's
true Did did you walk home today from
the temple yes is it summer yes did you
see all the bugs you stepped on to tell
you the truth I was looking at the stup
something I I didn't pay attention how
many ants I stepped on here but
logically do you think you might have
killed some ants yeah logically I
probably did okay those kinds of karma
are called un unaware
Karma it's not uh premeditated you don't
say uh after lunch I'm going to see how
many ants I can kill on the way home
nobody says that you don't get in your
car and say let's see how many bugs I
can squash you know nobody does that but
did you squash bu I don't
know probably I did okay so that's that
awareness is enough to plant the
seeds one seed two seeds then do the
math on your phone okay kill one bug
times two times two times two time two
time two 30 days later 200 million seeds
to die for me to die you see what I mean
so so karma is pernicious karma is nasty
stuff Karma doubles every day you got to
watch even small karmas okay you got to
watch even small Karm and you have to
confess even small karmas even if you
are
butter okay you gotta confess more
karmas by the way the other side of that
which is extremely
important is rejoicing okay you have you
are required by Buddhism to celebrate
the good stuff you do you are required
okay you're you're required to confess
your mistakes and you are goddamn
required to rejoice and celebrate the
good stuff you do and if you are
prejudice and you're always like oh I'm
such a bad person I got stuff to confess
you know I'm like you got anything to
tell me that's good no I can't think of
anything then you're not a
Buddhist okay a Buddhist has to give you
want to tell hear a story One More Story
okay so uh my teacher got an invitation
from the Catholic Church the local
Catholic Church uh can you come and give
a talk because the pope like 40 years
ago made a decision that all Catholics
should learn a little bit about other
religions and so we got an invitation to
go to this big Cathedral you know and uh
and and they asked my teacher to come
and talk he said sure I'd be happy to
talk about Buddhism and so we went there
and uh I had a little notebook in my
pocket when he had a good idea I had to
write it down so every time he had a
good idea he'd say Mike write this down
I do it with hagy
s uh he'd say Mike write this down so we
went into the that the priest said you
want to see the cathedral and my
teacher's like sure you know and we went
in and and we went halfway down the
we're going down the cathedral long big
Cathedral and my teacher's like what's
all those windows colored Windows
there's people in the windows what's
that and we said that's called stained
glass window you know and he said who's
the people and he says they are the
Saints and when people go to church they
can see the Saints in the stained glass
when he says mike take a
note we need stained glass windows of
Buddhist
Saints I'm like yeah okay I'm on it you
know we got it you know and uh he's like
hm what else he got here you know and
halfway down the halfway down the the
aisle long long aisle there was a little
room on the right side and U and we as
we are walking by AE priest in all the
robes you know he came in one door of
the room and this foxy
lady she goes in the other door of the
room and my teacher's
like and he says what's going
on and the priest said no don't worry
don't worry there's a divider they can't
touch each other he said well what is it
doing in there he said it's a confession
boot you know the the the priest goes in
he sits he waits people come and they go
on the other side of the window and they
say bless me I have sinned I made a
mistake and and he says well then what
happens and he said the priest tells the
person do this many Hail marries on your
Rosary you know and my teacher goes God
damn that's a good idea write that down
you know like WR the confession Booth
you know we need a confession booth in
our
he says oh and the the rosary thing
that's great for confession okay I got
it yeah yeah okay and then he goes to
the priest well where's the other one
you know and the priest is like what and
he goes where's the other room you know
yeah and he says what do you call this
thing it's a
confessional he says where's the
rejoicing
all and the the priest is like what and
he's like where's the rejoicing he says
what do you mean rejoicing where's the
little room where the priest comes in
and then you come in and you tell the
priest all the good stuff you did this
week and the priest is like let me make
a
note so anyway uh but it's human
nature that we don't Rejoice enough in
our Good Deeds we we can't stop thinking
about the mistakes we made in and but
it's human nature to ignore the good
things you're doing so so you got to
work on that okay you have a
Prejudice you you only think about the
sins you you did and you don't think
about all the sweet things you did
roughly for everybody it's 5050 I got
news for you
the best person on this planet and the
worst person on this planet are 1%
different really okay you don't get to
come to this planet if you're a really
good person okay and you don't get to
bad person the best person on this
planet and the worst person on this
planet are about 1% different okay and
we all we all make mistakes almost equal
number and we all do good things almost
equal number every evil person in this
world is doing a lot of sweet things
also okay and you have to you're
required to to sit in the rejoicing in
this tradition in this lineage you are
required to give it equal time and you
do not I I I promise you you do not okay
so when you're sitting there doing
medicine Buddha practice
you know tell them all your mistakes and
then say hey but I got some good stuff
too you know like I did a lot of sweet
stuff this week and as you do more and
more rejoice in all you will find more
and more good stuff you'll be shocked to
find out what a nice person you are okay
so give it equal time all right okay